When I run into a problem, instead of
being like, "All right, got to go talk
to the GraphQL team." I'm like, "Screw
it. I'm just going to figure out what
the problem is." This is Adam Ernst.
He's [music] a distinguished engineer or
IC9 at Meta who has built iOS
infrastructure that impacted the entire
company. And I asked them how his career
grew. If you show up, you're like, "Hey,
I did the work already for you." Much
easier conversation. 1,600 diffs in 6
months. Why did you spend so much time
also reviewing code? It's really
valuable because you can influence other
engineers in an organic way.
>> He was unusually honest about a major
failed project. So, component script was
interesting because it was a total and
complete failure and I worked on it for
like 2 years. With all that push back,
did you ever doubt the direction that
you're going in?
>> There were some literally sleepless
nights. Here's the full episode. [music]
I saw that you have something on your
resume. It says CosmicSoft, which
started in 2000. And if I have the math
right, that's like middle school for
you. So, what was that? And can you talk
more about the story behind Cosmicoft?
>> Yeah, you dug deep, man. I got to take
that off of there. That is indeed my
middle school software company. I
discovered at an early age that I liked
writing software. My mom was a teacher
and I would often spend time in her
classroom after school just like messing
around with computers and that gave me
the inspiration for my first product to
sell which was online testing software.
I wrote it in a tool called real basic
which was basically a crossplatform
visual basic inspired language. So I was
actually writing basic which oh god uh
and uh yeah sold it on the internet to
like tons of different countries. Uh it
was a lot of fun.
>> I was not a programmer at that time. Can
you give some more context? Is that
something that's running uh I guess
native on like a Windows machine or
something or what what is that? Well,
Real Basic was this this product from a
different company, not Microsoft. And it
was inspired by Visual Basic, very
clearly Visual Basicesque, but it was
crossplatform, meaning you could design
the software on any platform. I used a
Mac. The concept behind Visual Basic for
those who haven't used it is that you
basically had this like blank canvas and
you could just drag and drop buttons and
text fields and all this stuff on it.
Very easy to get into, right? Because
even nowadays with something like Swift
UI or React, you're writing code that
describes your user interface. There's a
separation there. Whereas Visual Basic,
you're like, well, I want a button,
drag, drop. Hm. When the button is
clicked, I want it to close the screen.
Okay, double click on the button. And
you write some code that's like
window.clo. Uh so really easy to get
started with, not very scalable and you
know basic is a horrifying language but
uh it was a fun way to get started and
really easy for me as basically a middle
schooler to write an actual software
product that was useful. How are you
selling that on the internet? Because at
the time they didn't have Stripe or
anything like that. Like how do you even
receive money from these people in other
countries?
>> There was a service called Eccelerate
which was like a prototype. It allowed
you to create an online store for your
software. It would help you create uh
you know like a code that you could
enter to unlock the software. And so
people would go to this website, they
type in their credit card info, and they
would get a code to unlock my software.
Fun fact, I also accepted payment via
check. So for a while as like an eighth
grader, I was getting checks from all
over the United States from teachers.
They'd mail me a check for 1995 and I
would send them via email a code to
unlock their software. Good times. Did
your parents know you were selling
software to strangers on the internet?
>> They did. I don't know what I don't know
what they thought of it or or or what
they could make of it, but they did know
I was doing it. [laughter]
>> Okay, that that's so cool. But yeah, let
let's get into kind of like the main
part of your career, which is um you
joining Facebook. You joined the company
to help with the native app rewrite from
HTML 5, and you got promoted to uh the
staff equivalent or E6 very fast. Were
you hired as a E5?
>> I'm pretty sure I was hired as an E5
because I had industry experience. I was
self-employed, but I, you know, like
wrote software in the industry for
iPhone. And yeah, it was funny because
Facebook was just a totally different
company. I joined just before the IPO,
like literally weeks before the IPO. And
so it was already a large company, but
compared to what it is today, totally
different. All of the iOS engineers
could meet in one conference room and
and we did, right? like every week we
had a a stand up and like we talked
through what we did that week and all
that stuff and yeah it was a fun time to
join because we were totally rewriting
the app. There was this cultural shift
away from face web this like HTML 5
attempt at making a native app and
towards the native code and the native
engineers were very much like ascendant
right like we had we had won the battle
and now we were we needed to prove
ourselves that it was going to work out
and it did and that also meant a lot of
big pro uh a lot of big opportunities a
lot of big problems that needed solving
because our codebase was brand new and
we were discovering all the ways where
it was going to fall over as we
continued making the app bigger adding
new features
So that's what I walked into in 2012 and
it was definitely a fun time.
>> One of the first projects that you
worked on was one of those scaling
challenges in adopting native code and
that also happened to be your E6 promo.
Could you talk a little bit about the
core data problem and you know why it
was E6?
>> Yeah, core data is Apple's OM database
framework. It's great if you are a
startup that has like two engineers and
you just need a small little way to
store data. It works great for that. We
already had, like I said, we had enough
iOS engineers we could all fit in one
conference room. So, we started with
like 15 to 20 maybe by the time I got
there. And we were rapidly growing,
right? Like soon we had 100, soon we had
200. Core data falls over completely at
that scale. So, we needed to swap out
how we store data. But this was also a
really critical time, right? We had at
this point just launched our native
rewrite using core data and so everyone
wanted to add features. The groups team,
the events team, the pages team, they
all wanted to like rewrite their stuff
in native and get all the great wins
from native code. Meanwhile, we on the
on at that time we mobile was a separate
org inside of Facebook. We on the mobile
team were like uh this is not going so
well. Like cord data is going to fall
over tomorrow and everyone's knocking
down our door being like please rewrite
native. So we had to find a way to do it
incrementally. we needed to find a a
better architecture which was what we
you know found along the way. So that's
where we were in like 2012 2013 and we
called our new solution mem models which
was an immutable model system which made
it a lot easier to reason about thread
safety mutations etc.
>> You had this new offering that you know
had a lot of benefits to it but still I
imagine you had to convince other teams
to adopt it. So, you know, the core
features of the app, feed, etc. were
already bought in because the
performance was miles better and they
didn't require any convincing. It was
driving it all the way to the finish
line. Getting the last regular products
to onboard that was harder, right?
Because for them, they were like, "Yeah,
so our performance is a little bit
better. Who cares? We don't care. We
we're more interested in other things."
Also, it wasn't necessarily individual
teams that were skeptical of the entire
project. But there we did get a lot of
push back from Apple engineers for a
lack of a better word like engineers who
believe in Apple's built-in solutions
and are like why would we not use core
data like I'm an iOS engineer we should
use core data and everything else
vanilla from Apple. I think that's
lesson to someone over the years just
because meta and Facebook and Instagram
and all of our other properties have
gotten so large it's clear that Apple's
solutions don't scale to that size. But
at least in 2012 and 2013, there was
there were a lot of people still
clinging to this idea that hey, we
should just use the vanilla Apple
frameworks and we needed to convince
them over and over and over like here's
why that's just not going to work. So
that was a big challenge for us at the
time.
>> What did you learn about influencing
other engineers without uh authority and
do you have any tips on how to do that
across like a large code base?
>> My number one tip is talk in person or
via video conference if possible. you
spend a lot of time trying to make your
writing clear and accessible and have a
good tone and you can often convey that
tone way faster in person. My other
feedback is to be sympathetic to their
point of view, right? Like my I would
always start the conversation saying
like, "Yes, I prefer vanilla Apple
frameworks too. We're not going down
this path just because I want to invent
a new framework. Here are the specific
reasons why we think it can't scale.
Give data. give actual you know we were
getting to the point where we were
disassembling core data's source code
because it's not open source to
understand what is it doing why is it
taking so long to initialize having that
data to give to other engineers is
really useful right like hey you don't
know how core data works because it's a
black box we know how it works here's
how it works and that's why that's not
going to work for us so you know I guess
that sums up as do your research so that
you can be convincing in that fashion
and the final one for me personally is
just do the work for them. I think there
are some engineers who would go about
this project in the sense of hey I built
this scaffolding now my job is to
convince other people to do the work of
migration. We call this code archetype
coding machine. I have mixed feelings
about archetypes in general but like in
general the idea is like I write a lot
of code. I like to write code. So my
thought was I'll just go do it for them.
It's one thing to convince them hey you
have to step up and do all this work.
The other is like if you show up you're
like hey I did the work already for you.
Here are the benefits. I just need you
to sign off and say yes, this is fine in
our codebase. Much easier conversation.
That mode of operation was very
successful here at Meta for a long time.
I think it's getting harder now. Our
codebase is so big that one person can't
necessarily do the entire migration. You
require some more alignment, but for a
long time that was a very good way to
operate because you just show up and be
like, "Hey, I solved the problem." And
people be like, "Great, love that you
solved the problem." And then I have to
do nothing. I just say yes. Worked
really well. I saw like in the career
note that you wrote about this promotion
that you'd also reviewed over 1,600
uh diffs in a half and that comes out to
around like 14 diffs per workday. Why
did you spend so much time also
reviewing code?
I think code review is super undervalued
and I still do a ton of it. It's really
valuable because you can influence other
engineers in an organic way, right?
Someone's like, "Adam, what's your
message to other engineers at the
company? What do you want to change?"
I'm like, "I I don't know." But if I see
a concrete diff and I'm like, "I don't
like how they're doing this and here's
why." It gives me a perfect opening to
to get into it. However, I also try to
be a very flexible different reviewer,
right? I feel like there were some
different reviewers who had that
attitude of like, I'm going to help
other engineers and then they were very
inflexible. Anytime they saw any little
thing they didn't like, reject. My view
was like, "All right, I see what you're
doing and why you're doing it this way.
Here's my concern." And then either
like, "I'm gonna let you do what you
want if you really feel strongly, but
here's what I would do differently next
time." Or I'd be like, "Let's talk about
how to redo your work to accomplish
whatever concern I have." basically hold
their hand through the process if if I
can because I feel like that's a great
way to, you know, now they're gonna
hopefully if they're convinced by my
argument, they're going to hold that
same change in how they operate for
their own future work and in all the
future code review they do. It's like
viral, right? And you see this would
would spread through the code reviews
that they did. So, I thought it was a
really great way to like get my opinions
out there and have those debates in a
really structured format.
>> Given that you've done just such an
absurd volume of diff reviews, what
makes a good diff comment versus a bad
one in your opinion?
>> Talk through why you care about what you
are nitpicking and not just what to
change, right? Don't say change X to Y.
Say, hey, X has some problems, so I
really want you to use Y instead. But if
you really feel strongly if there's
something I'm missing, then you can go
ahead and use X. Right? The other thing
I was always open to in different review
comments was the fact that I might be
missing context. And that's still the
diff author's fault, maybe because like
your diff should contain enough context
for anyone to review it on its own
merits, but I'd often be like, "Hey, I
don't understand why you're doing it
this way. I want you to do it this way
instead, but is there some missing
context that would change my mind? If
so, fill me in and put it in your diff
summary." which again I feel like makes
sure that if I'm making a stupid mistake
which happens I don't look like a total
idiot who's just like getting it wrong.
It really helps. So moving on to like
you know E7 promo or the senior staff
promo. I know that the main project that
kind of drove that was component kit.
Can you give some context on the story
behind component kit?
>> The years all blur together at this
point but this was like 2014 maybe. We
had a very large and complex product,
Facebook newsfeed, which was growing and
growing and growing so fast because the
company hired lots of new engineers and
they stuffed everyone on newsfeed
because that was the hot product at the
time. So it was basically falling apart,
right? We had constant crashes, constant
layout bugs where like content would be
overlapping in weird ways and it was a
struggle to keep performance good. I
can't claim credit for the idea again
here. It was Lee Byron who was I think
my manager at the time but was for a
long time a very senior engineer at the
company and co-invented GraphQL and he
had done a lot of work with React on the
web which was relatively new then too
even on the web it was new and he was
like you know what we really need this
React concept but for iOS development at
this time React Native either didn't
exist or was just a prototype and so Lee
told me like why don't you just take
some time and think about how would the
concepts of react work in an iOS first
way and component kit was my answer to
that question. So it uses the same
concepts of like components
immutability, rerender everything
conceptually at least when anything
changes
view reconciliation, right? So you're
not directly managing UI views. You're
instead just stating, hey, I want there
to be a button that has this caption.
The framework takes care of creating the
actual button view. And I'm pretty proud
of the balance that it struck in terms
of the syntax was appealing, the
performance was amazing, and it allowed
us to solve a problem that we really
needed to solve as a business. And
again, this was 2014, so years before
Swift UI. Swift didn't exist yet. Swift
UI didn't exist yet. React Native didn't
exist yet. It was a very early on the
scene. And it did take some convincing
of other iOS engineers because it was
still a very alien way to write code on
iOS. But once convinced, everybody loved
it. Everybody thought this is a really
great way to write the UI for a complex
product like Facebook newsfeed. So the
big challenge there was inventing the
framework, getting it adopted in
newsfeed and then getting it adopted
everywhere else. So I had lots of lots
of work to do. How did you convince
people because you know this declarative
framework was such a different way of
doing things. I imagine there was a lot
of push back. How did you you drive
those difficult conversations?
Tons of push back. Um some people were
convinced when they saw concrete
examples of hey here's what the same
code would look like in component kit.
It's now like a third as much code. Some
people were convinced when they could
see the performance, right? Oh, look, it
allows us to render all the viewed
hierarchies on a background thread and
then only do the minimal amount of work
on the main thread. And they were like,
that's really cool. But there were
plenty of people who were hold outs even
then and we had to call in mediators,
right? Basically, like there were other
senior engineers at the time because
when I was inventing component kit, I
was an IC6. there were other more senior
engineers who would you know get us to
huddle up and try to talk through how do
we find a path forward that we can all
agree on and I think Lee Byron was very
involved in these conversations. I know
uh Alan Kennaro was a senior engineer at
the time who was very involved in this
helping us like mediate between these
different groups but I think the fact
that React had a lot of cred as a
framework at the company on the web
really helped right because we could
point and be like look at what React is
doing on the web. We want to do the same
on iOS. There aren't any really good
reasons why we can't do it. It's not
impossible to do on the platform. We we
have proven we can. So get on board. And
I acknowledge the downsides of component
kit, right? It's by now it's very creaky
and old because it was a C++ objective
C++ framework. Now we have a Swift API
for it. That's great. But still at the
time the weirdnesses of component kit
were even then somewhat unappealing. But
my pitch was always, yes, it's a little
weird. It's not the usual way of writing
code in iOS, but here's all the amazing
things we get. That's why you should do
it. So that's the pitch that we had to
make again and again and again to
skeptical iOS engineers. Is there
anything that you learned in trying to
convince these people that were very
against this this approach that is kind
of useful and general learning for
anyone that's trying to have some new
developer offering and convince people
to use it? Allies are super useful,
right? Um, I still remember uh there
were some engineers like Clement Gendmer
and Greg Mech who carried a lot of
weight in the company and they saw it
and liked it. So great, I wasn't alone
and they could help convince other
people because, you know, I have one way
of convincing people which isn't always
effective and they have other ways of
convincing people which often were more
effective. And so it was nice to be able
to break it down and like, you know, see
the different ways that this discussion
happened over time. There were
opportunities for compromise. The other
big alternative out there was this
framework called panels which hadn't
really gotten off the ground yet but was
supposed to be like the next way to
write UI at Facebook and I knew them
really well because one of them was like
my mentor and so I you know was very
very close to Jonathan Dan the guy
behind panels and boy they had a really
hard time because they felt like they
were developing the next thing and then
I came along was like actually let's do
component kit wasn't so good but we
found a way to compromise and we adopted
some of the panels data source
technology to power component kit which
was a good compromise and allowed us all
to feel like we had a win. Instead of
sticking to your guns and every little
thing, if you can find a way to bring
people into your fold, into the tent,
that's really really helpful.
>> With all that push back, did you ever
doubt the direction that you're going
in?
>> No, I was very convinced that this was
the right call for Facebook newsfeed. I
will say, and this goes for all
declarative UI frameworks, React, Swift
UI, component kit. They're really good
at some things, like a Facebook newsfeed
is the perfect thing for it because it's
like a scrolling list of complicated
multi-level nesting and it's mostly
static, right? There's some animation
and cool stuff, but mostly it just is
like a list of stuff. That's the perfect
application for it. When you look at
like a super dynamic drag and drop
interface, h maybe not the right thing
for it, right? Maybe not the ideal case
anyway. you can make it work, but it's
not going to be incredibly natural. So,
I'm very aware that like there are
trade-offs to these different paradigms.
And I wasn't drinking the Kool-Aid in
terms of telling everyone component
kit's the only way to write UIs on
Facebook. Like that should be the, you
know, our only option is component kit.
Uh, no. But in general, for what we
wanted to use it for, yes, I was very
convinced that it was the right path
forward. You know, the next project you
worked on was component script. What was
the motivation behind that project? And
you know what's the story behind it?
>> So component script was interesting
because it was a total and complete
failure and I worked on it for like two
years. At the time, my manager was a guy
named Ari Grant who was a force of
nature, right? He was like all over the
place, very busy,
carried a lot of influence. And Ari felt
really strongly that we needed to get
out of the perplatform silo, right? So
like iOS had component kit, Android had
a React and Component kit inspired by
then called WHO. But this meant we were
writing everything multiple times,
right? We had to write it in component
kit for iOS, we had to write it in
Android. He wanted to have a
crossplatform solution. React Native was
not that solution and we knew that at
this time we had tried React Native and
it didn't go well. The reason was in my
opinion, this is just my opinion, React
Native is designed to be in charge of
the entire app. It works really well if
your entire app is React Native or if
you have entire app React Native and
then small little pieces on the very
bottom are native or bridged. Where it
doesn't work is the way we wrote
software at that time which was we had
this large complex native app and we
wanted to slot in small pieces of
crossplatform in different areas right
so like oh maybe this little square on
this screen is rendered using JavaScript
maybe this tab is rendered in JavaScript
and this tab is native React Native
could not do that for us at the time
they've done a lot of architectural
changes to React Native in the last 10
years since then and maybe it's better
at it now but at the
didn't really work. So we wanted
crossplatform. We knew React Native was
not it. What could we do? And so Ari
asked me to go and work on this. And I
at the time it was like okay this is the
next nudge, right? Like we Byron nudged
me to work on React for iOS. That was
component kit. Great. This is the next
nudge work on crossplatform for our UI
rendering frameworks that we use on iOS
and Android. And so I came up with a
framework called component script. The
idea was basically at first I took the
React APIs, the actual React
implementation. I said, "What if we just
made a different React Native, right?"
So exactly like React Native except that
it works on top of component kit and
width because that's what we already
have. This turned out to be too
difficult. React had a really large
surface area and a very complex surface
area and trying to make that work on on
component kit and with it was too
challenging. So I was like, "All right,
I'll do a smaller paired down API that
feels just like React, but actually is
simpler and make that work on top of
component kit and litho." And I made it
work. It was a real framework. People
built real features on it. You could
build full screens. You could build
individual units. You could do all kinds
of, you know, birectional embeddings.
You could have a native screen that had
a component script unit which had a
native component inside of that. You
could have a component script screen
which had a native section. All this
stuff, really cool features.
And for me, it was a real learning
experience because I learned that just
because it was technically excellent
didn't mean it was going to win. It
checked all the boxes we needed in terms
of interop and type safety, but it
didn't win and didn't come close to
winning because there were many other
factors that I didn't take into account.
So, a great example of writing a lot of
code and doing a lot of technical work
doesn't mean that it's going to win. I
mean, if we were to kind of postmortem
why it didn't win, what are the things
that you did well and what are the
things that maybe could have gone
better?
>> Um, I mean, doing well, I just mentioned
it did check it checked all the
technical boxes that we as in like the
core product infra group cared about,
right? Like it was type safe. It
integrated with GraphQL and component
kit and WHO, our existing native
frameworks. It was birectional. So, you
would never be suddenly cut off. There
would never be a point where you're
like, "Oh, I just need to embed this
native component and I can't do it." No,
you could always do it. The mistakes
were number one, I wasn't really aiming
at a particular target engineer, right?
So, React Native was focused on like web
engineers who wanted to write for
mobile. Component kit was focused on,
hey, we have iOS engineers that already
know how to write iOS code. Let's let
them write iOS code, but have excellent
performance.
Component script is like, hey, you can
write JavaScript, but it's not React.
So, like iOS engineers were like, I
don't want to learn a whole new
language. I don't want to learn
JavaScript. And JavaScript engineers
were like, I'll use React Native. I
don't want to touch this like weird not
React API. No thank you. So, we were
kind of stuck. Number two is that like
we on the product infrastructure group
really cared about GraphQL. We were
like, hey, we want data consistency
everywhere. So, this framework needs to
be based on GraphQL. But it turns out
GraphQL can be kind of a pain sometimes,
right? Especially at that time, GraphQL
tooling was slow and a lot of uh a lot
of hassle. We've fixed it a lot since
then, but at the time it was bad. And so
trying to build on top of this slow,
janky native GraphQL stack really slowed
us down. Meanwhile, there was another
framework out there that was, you know,
coming in with a server-driven sort of
UI approach. And their solution was
like, don't worry about data
consistency.
What if we just didn't do it? And we
were all horrified. were like, "What?
You don't have data consistency?" So, if
you like a post on one screen and you go
to another screen, it won't show you
that the post is liked. And the answer
was yes. 60% of the time, 80% of the
time, products just don't care. And for
the 20% that do care, you could hack
something in there that makes it work.
So, we were pretty horrified by not
using GraphQL, but it that was a huge
advantage if you could just skip all
that stuff. But, I refused to compromise
and that was a problem. And then
finally, I went really wide. I was like,
"All right, I'm just going to talk to
all engineers, all mobile engineers, and
be like, you guys should all try out
component script." And this meant that I
got little pings of interest all over
the place. Because there were a few
engineers here and there that were like,
"Sure, I'll try JavaScript. Sure, I'll
try crossplatform." But there wasn't any
individual team that was like, "Yes,
this is how we want to write products
from now on." And so that meant that it
never went anywhere, right? Individual
engineers would try individual little
things here and there, but that was not
going to get any momentum. Funny thing
was just when I finally pulled the plug
on component script the group's team was
like oh we just decided we were going to
go all in on component script and I was
like oh man no [laughter] u but even
that would not have been enough momentum
right it was too little too late so you
wrote about this retrospection it's you
know very detailed one of the best you
know retrospectives I've I've read why
did you publish that so publicly what
was the motivation behind it
>> I don't recall it might have been
encouraged that I write it, but I
certainly wanted to write it. It was
cathartic to talk about what went wrong.
And even at the time, I had a
reputation, right? People who knew who I
was. So, everyone would always be like,
"Hey, how's that component script thing
going?" And the postmortem was a
convenient way for me to rip the
band-aid off and be candid about, "Hey,
it didn't work and here's why." And not
have to constantly rehash that
conversation over and over and over. Um,
but also I hope that it would influence
the way that people did stuff at the
company in the future, right? Like
hopefully no one made the same mistake
after that if they read my postmortem or
at least they were aware of what they
were walking into. And you know in this
case you drove a very ambitious project
and it did fail in the end when it comes
to performance reviews in a half where
something like this is happening or a
year where something like this is
happening. How does that play out and
should people be worried about you know
their projects getting cancelled or
things like that?
>> The thing that made me realize it needed
to be cancelled is that I got a meets
most. So performance did its job there.
>> My manager at the time did the right
thing and was like this is not working.
>> He was also a new manager for me. So I
think he like
>> could see it with fresh eyes and be like
this is not going to work. And then when
I did cancel it, I like to think I did
it in the right way, which is there were
products and features written in
component script and I helped those
teams migrate back to native code or to
react native or whatever they wanted and
I completely deleted the framework. I
didn't weave it as like, you know, oh,
this one product is still on component
script, so we have to weave it around
forever and someone will have to clean
it up someday. No, I was like, I'm
driving this all the way and I'm
deleting the code is going to be gone
from the repo, which I think garnered
some goodwill because it showed others
this is the right way to clean up after
your mess. Um, so I feel like I got in
if anything a positive bump after the
fact, right? Like there was enough
relief of like, all right, this showed
people how to wind up wind down a
project that isn't working out. and he
posted publicly about it show talking
about the lessons learned and there's no
mass left behind. So if anything I feel
like it helped in the in the immediate
aftermath. So if anyone is like staring
down the barrel of like I think my
framework's not going well but I'm
afraid to kill it. You might get more
goodwill from killing it responsibly
than just like dragging it out and
constantly waiting until it's too late.
Were there signs that like looking back
you could have maybe avoided some of the
pain of I don't know meets most or you
know kind of like it going on as long as
it did.
>> Yeah. I mean look there were there was
it was a two-year project and for the
last year I knew it wasn't going right
and I should have listened to my gut,
right? I there were some literally
sleepless nights. Not a lot but like
some where I was like this is it doesn't
feel right. It's not going well. I don't
understand what to do. And I'm a coding
machine. So my reaction was I just need
to write more code. I just need to help
more features convert and it'll suddenly
take off. And I should have listened
instead to that part of my gut that was
telling me this is not going to work
out. Just go do something you love and
find a different way to have impact and
uh that would have been much better for
me in the short and long run.
>> You said before that you know for sure
you you never wanted to try management
and it was not right for you. Um, for
someone who's considering that kind of
decision, how did you know that
management's not right for you?
>> I like writing code. I really like
writing code a lot. And as a manager,
you can't write codes. So, I mean, for
me, it's a no-brainer, right? I'm also
just I'm
less good at the non-code related parts
of the job. So, like driving alignment
and writing docs, I'm just not good at
that stuff. And so, for me, I'm like,
yeah, I don't want to touch that. And
finally, I feel like I'm very good at
communication with other engineers in a
technical role. Like I'm very good at
like, hey, we need to solve this
technical problem. Let's all get on the
same page about how to solve it. I don't
think I'm as good at doing that when I'm
not quite when I'm more removed from the
problem, right? Managers have to lot of
do a lot of direction setting and
influencing people without directly
pointing to like this line of code is
the problem and that I think I'm less
good at. So for me, I always knew
management is not for me. Uh but it
depends on the person. Obviously, I'm a
pretty extreme case.
>> What about um picking the domain that
you went with? So, from what I see in
your career, it's almost entirely on the
iOS side with some crossplatform work.
Well, how did you align on iOS? And is
that something that you feel strongly
about being tied to or is that just
where things have taken you?
>> That's where things have taken me. I
don't change around a lot. I've never
really changed teams once at this
company, right? like I've like been
shifted on to different teams as part of
reorgs, but I don't know. I just kind of
roll with the punches and I like what
I'm doing. I feel like I like the team,
so why mess it up? I admire engineers
that are like, you know what, I want to
go see what this AI thing is about. I'm
going to go check it out. Or like, oh
man, I really want to go work on ARVR.
That's not me. I knew I liked mobile and
I felt like I was getting the right
opportunities to work on stuff I cared
about. So, I just kept rolling with it.
And I think it has worked out really
well for me because it allowed me to
build deep knowledge expertise about how
all different parts of our system work.
Right? If you want to know the guts of
the graphical codegen or value object
generation or buck or all these things,
I know what's up. And so it's really
helped me get really deep in this
particular domain. And that means I have
a lot of knowledge about it that helps
answer questions from others. Very
useful. Would I do mobile if I was a
brand new engineer today? Maybe not.
Maybe I do AI because that seems like
the hot stuff, right? Or I don't know
what else. Uh but I don't feel too bad
about sticking with it. You you talked
about the technical depth. Let's say
someone's goal was to be like you. They
they really wanted to, you know, super
aggressively pursue the high IC career
path. They want to go IC9 or bust. Do
you think that technical depth is better
than breath for becoming the highest
levels of uh senior IC? I I mean it
depends on how you operate. I've seen
lots of different engineers that operate
in different ways. I will say I have
breath and depth, right? As in like not
that you know it's perfect. It's not
like I only know mobile though, right?
Like I know ex a lot about how buck
operates. I know a lot about how uh
GraphQL
schema works. And so for me, the thing
that helped me personally worked for me,
maybe not for everyone, when I run into
a problem, instead of being like, "All
right, got to go talk to the GraphQL
team." I'm like, "Screw it. I'm just
going to figure out what the problem is.
I'm going to dive eight levels deep into
their codegen guts until I find the
problem and then I'll either fix it
myself and now I know GraphQL codegen or
I will show up to the GraphQL team and
I'll be like hey ran into this problem
debugged it eight levels deep here's the
problem how do I fix it which impresses
the GraphQL team means that I'm not
taking up all their time and I've
learned something new about a new system
and if you keep doing that enough then
you will discover a lot about a lot of
different systems and you'll understand
them and that'll give you so much
knowledge and so much it's like a
superpower to be able to dive into all
these systems that you now know. It's
also organic, right? We talked before
about code review and how if you just
review code that organically gives you
actual discussions about how do we want
to write our code? Same thing with this,
right? Instead of being like, hm, which
systems do I need to go learn for my
job? I'm like, they'll come to me,
right? I'm going to have a problem that
I run into. GraphQL is going to block my
code from landing. Great. Now I have a
reason to go delve into GraphQL code
genen. I'm not gonna study it from first
principles and be like well I should go
learn the graphical code genen systems
just because but when it comes up sure
I'll do that. A lot of people that get
promoted to these really high levels.
One thing I've noticed is the the
expectations become I guess scarier and
scarier for people or they they they get
there and they kind of get worried that
they can meet expectations. You know for
you as a IC9 and you're you're writing
code. How do you make sure that it's,
you know, IC9 code? Like there's this
does it, you don't worry about that.
I've flipped the switch off. I just
don't care. Uh I used to worry about
that too a lot. And then I was like, you
know what? I'm just going to do what I
love and I'm going to check in my check
in with my manager often to make sure
that I'm solving problems that need
solving, right? I'm not just going to go
work on something that doesn't matter.
But as long as I'm working on what's
important for my org and I like what I'm
doing, I'm just not going to worry about
it and I'm going to do it. And that has
served me really well, right? Uh
component script being the ex exception
where like eventually it was no longer
important for the company or the or that
was like someone needed to prod me to
realize that. But they prodded me and I
realized it and the problem was solved,
right? Like in some sense like getting a
meets most was freeing in the sense of
like well if that happens again I'll
know that like I went too deep and too
hard and didn't listen and now I go
listen and fix it. So yeah, my answer is
I just flip the switch off and don't
worry about it because that's
counterproductive. as a you know senior
IC you you are in forums with other
senior IC's and also you have a
viewpoint that others don't which you
could see what uh work is technically
difficult and exceptional you know what
are some other engineers that you think
are exceptional and what in your opinion
makes their work exceptional
>> I've got a list so I'm going to go down
the list
>> okay
>> I really admire Dustin Shahitapor who's
an engineer who works very much like me
he writes a lot of code. That's the part
of the job he enjoys. He and I have a
very similar working style. So, for that
reason, I get along with him great. Uh,
another engineer that I've worked on for
worked with for a very, very long time
is Wei Han, who joined the company on
the same day I did in 2012. Uh, and our
careers often over overlapped. We worked
together on a lot of things, including
component script for a while. And she is
many different archetypes. She does not
fit in one box, but she's she's more of
a fixer. She's very good at like, hey,
this metric is not right. what is the
deal? Which is something I can kind of
do, but she can really do. And so I love
someone that can dive. Again, it's like
diving 10 layers into systems you don't
know and figuring out what the hell is
going on here. She's great at that. He's
no longer with our comp with Meta, but
Michael Bolan was always an engineer I
looked up to because he was a great
project starter. He could identify the
need. Hey, we need a fuzzy file searcher
that works on in insanely large repos.
What do we do? He kickstarted a project
called Miles and just did it, right?
which is like backend binaries on a
multiple platforms, deployment,
documentation, naming, all this stuff
that he could just do and he did it over
and over and over again. That's just one
of the many things he started. I think
he started buck too. Let's see here. Bob
Baldwin is a very senior product
engineer. I mean, I think he works on
Inferno now, but for a long time he was
on product and he's an excellent
communicator. He can really boil down
the message, which is something I think
a lot of engineers very much struggle
with and it's a really important skill
is writing and communication. So I
really admired his communication and how
he could make things clear. Another
engineer that's similar is Oliver Ricard
who uh is a very very good writer and a
very good communicator and his posts are
absolute masterworks. Whenever someone
is like hey my engineer needs to work on
communication I'm like go look at
Oliver's posts. That's the bar. That's
what you should be aiming for.
And finally I'm aware of what I'm not
the skills that I'm missing. So another
senior engineer that I work with almost
every day is Nolan O'Brien. uh and he is
like my polar opposite. He writes code
but not a not a whole lot. He is
extremely good at driving alignment
between different teams and he's
extremely good at managing the Apple
relationship which is something I never
had patience to do, right? Like Meta and
Apple, they don't always get along.
Nolan finds a way to communicate between
these two companies and try to get us on
the same page, focus on what we can do
together. And I I really admire him for
that. So that's my list of other senior
engineers I really really admire.
>> The last thing that I'd like to ask you
is you have a lot of, you know,
experience at this point. And if you
were to go back to yourself right when
you had graduated Princeton and give
yourself some career advice, what would
you say?
>> Nothing. It worked out pretty well for
me. I'm not screwing with it, man.
[laughter]
Um, the funny thing is when I was
graduating Princeton in 2010, I thought
about applying. I was like, should I be
self-employed and write iPhone apps or
should I go work for a company? And I
actually applied to Facebook. And I'm
pretty sure at the time what they would
do is they would send you this puzzle.
They'd send you like a mysterious puzzle
that you had to like solve the mystery
and then you could apply. And I threw it
in the trash. I was like, I don't have
time for that. I'm not doing that. Uh,
and so I'm like, what if I joined
Facebook in 2010? What would that have
been like? It probably would have been a
lot worse because I would have been
around for all the HTML 5 stuff and I
would have just been like, oh no, no,
no. Um, but yeah, I I don't think I
would offer any advice to myself at the
time because uh my personal situation
worked out really well. Um, as far as
general career advice, I don't know, do
what you like, right? Like I feel like
it's really hard to fake enthusiasm or
like find enthusiasm for something you
really don't enjoy doing. So like find
what you love doing and do that. Uh, and
if that intersects with what the
industry needs, you're in a really lucky
place. You know, I used to always hear
that advice and think that is uh cliche
and
>> it's very cliche.
>> Yeah. But actually there's so much stuff
downstream of that like your
productivity comes from you loving the
work. I mean you have insane uh output
and your curiosity and the learning it's
got to be order of magnitude more than
it would be if you hated it and you
didn't proactively dig you know 10
layers deep. So,
>> I think it's good if you if you like
solving problems. That's the thing,
right? Because it's not like every
single moment I'm debugging some really
bad code deep in some awful system. I'm
loving what I'm doing. But I like the
challenge of solving problems. And so,
if you like that, you're in good you're
in a good place.
>> Thanks so much for your time, Adam. I
really appreciate it. Um I was really
looking forward to talking to you. So,
thanks so much for sharing your career
story with the community.
>> Sure thing. Thanks, Ryan.
>> Thank you for listening to the podcast.
It's a passion project of mine that I've
really enjoyed building. Another passion
project that I've been working on kind
of in secret is building an ergonomic
keyboard that I wish existed and I
finally have a prototype. So, I'd love
to show you what we've built. It's ultra
lowprofile and ergonomic and I couldn't
find anything like it on the market. So,
that's why we built it. I'll put a link
to the keyboard in the description. You
can take a look and learn more about the
project there. We could definitely use
your support. Also, if you have any
feedback for me about the show, I'd love
to hear it. Comments on YouTube have led
to guests coming on like Ilia Gregoric
and David Fowler. I wasn't aware of them
until someone dropped a comment. Also,
feedback in the comments helped me learn
to reduce the number of cliffhers in the
intros. So, your comments definitely
make a difference. Please keep letting
me know what you'd like to see more of
in the show, and I'll see you in the
next episode.